<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Compassionate Path</title>
    <description></description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Sat, 05 Sep 2015 20:51:07 -0400</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 05 Sep 2015 20:51:07 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Hillerman Country</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/img/shiprock2.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;fullwidth&quot; src=&quot;/img/shiprock2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Even before moving to New Mexico, I loved Tony Hillerman novels. There I was on a farm in Northern Wisconsin in January–below zero,  snow on the ground– reading Hillerman’s descriptions of Shiprock, Window Rock, Gallup and the terrain and open sky of the Southwest. Now the mystery series has been continued by his daughter, Anne, and I just finished reading her first novel, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Spider-Womans-Daughter-Leaphorn-Novel/dp/0062270494/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1441487703&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=spider+womans+daughter&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Spider Woman’s Daughter&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. One of the main characters is Officer Bernie Manuelito who worries about a mother who is old and frail, a sister who is drinking heavily (and to Bernie’s eyes wasting her life), an uncle who has been shot in the head and in a coma in Santa Fe, and the investigation of that shooting which seems to be going nowhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This morning I thought, &lt;em&gt;Good grief, What a life she has!&lt;/em&gt;  Where is there room for joy and happiness? Then I thought we all have similar lives filled with worry and stress. Worrying about the health of our parents, our own health, the well-being of our children. Stressing over our job, money, our relationships. We have an over-abundance of things to worry and stress about that can keep us occupied 24/7. And this worry acts as a filter to the present moment. We think about our worries instead of clearly seeing what is in front of us. We might be out walking our dog but our minds are regurgitating on the latest hassles at work which fill us with a slight anger. We might be sitting with our parents in their living room but our minds are off weaving a story of how frail they look which fills us with worry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the Hillerman novel was focused on just recounting the internal worries of Bernie Manuelito it would be a pretty boring read. Instead, Bernie often stops the internal yakking to appreciate where she is. At times she is present in the moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Finally, the view she loved, the San Juan River south of the highway, flowing between rows of towering ancient cottonwoods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The sky was majestic. The Sandia Mountains rose like a rugged blue monolith to the east, glowing in the reflected oranges, vivid reds, and brilliant sunflower hues of the sunset. He put his arm around her as they watched the light change from magenta to smoky rose and dissolve into the soft gray of summer predarkness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We too can work toward being present in the moment. We can be present with our parents in their living room without some distracting constant dialog in our minds. We can walk the dog and simply be walking our dog. Instead of thinking &lt;em&gt;Good grief, my life is so hard. I work long hours, I’m exhausted when I get home. blah, blah, blah.&lt;/em&gt; we can just be present in the moment. That’s where happiness lies. Our lives may indeed be hard. We may work long hours. We may have some illness. But by constantly thinking about all this we are just working ourselves up more and more. More anger, more worry, more suffering. The path out of this is working on being present in the moment. This is the focus of Zen and why we practice meditation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 02 Sep 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/posts/2015/09/Hillerman.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/posts/2015/09/Hillerman.html</guid>
        
        <category>knitr</category>
        
        <category>servr</category>
        
        <category>httpuv</category>
        
        <category>websocket</category>
        
        
        <category>jekyll</category>
        
        <category>rstats</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Dogen &amp; Adyashanti</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Last week, a member of our group, Eve, mentioned &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adyashanti&quot;&gt;Adyashanti&lt;/a&gt;, a person I had never heard of before. After the meetup I went online and read his free booklet &lt;a href=&quot;https://d1c742hwzmv7ke.cloudfront.net/library/The_Way_of_Liberation_Ebook.pdf&quot;&gt;The Way of Liberation&lt;/a&gt;. In it he writes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“To study The Way of Liberation teachings is to study yourself. To study yourself does not mean to add more knowledge to your cluttered brain’s ideas about yourself, but to remove all of the customary defining characteristics you usually associate self with: name, race, gender, occupation, social status, past, as well as all of the psychological judgments you make about yourself. When the self is stripped down to its essential core, all that can be said about it is: “I am; I exist.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This seems like a modern version of a core teaching in Soto Zen written by its founder, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/D%C5%8Dgen&quot;&gt;Zen Master Dogen&lt;/a&gt;, in the 12 century:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“To study the Buddha Way is to study the self. To study the self is to forget the self. To forget the self is to be actualized by myriad things. When actualized by myriad things, your body and mind, as well as the body and mind of others drop away. No trace of realization remains, and this no-trace continues endlessly.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It might be helpful to replace ‘to study the buddha way’ with ‘to wake up’: To wake up is to study the self. In studying the self we begin to realize there is no unique unchanging self. There is nothing we can point to and say There, that bit, that’s uniquely me, me, me. Every thought we have is a product of a vast collection of encounters we have had with others and a host of other events. There’s a bit of your grandfather in you, a bit of your first love, that women that made a funny face at you when you were five, the sloppy kiss of your neighbor’s dog. There’s a trace of emotion still in you from that guy that cut you off in traffic earlier today and from the guy that did the same last week. Innumerable events have shaped your mind. The same with your body. Everything in your body existed before you were born. Thich Nhat Hanh says there are clouds and sun in you as they help create the food you ate to sustain yourself. In studying the self, we see we are part of a vast net of experiences—we are actualized by myriad things. And “when actualized by myriad things, your body and mind, as well as the body and mind of others drops away.” Once we have this realization and become awake, then what? Dogen says we forget about it and get on with our daily life, but with a difference—we live our ordinary life being awake, seeing things as they truly are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;one-way-to-study-the-self-is-to-sit-zazen&quot;&gt;One way to study the self is to sit zazen.&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jun 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/posts/2015/06/Dogen.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/posts/2015/06/Dogen.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Drawing Circles</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/img/EnsoZen.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;fullwidth&quot; src=&quot;/img/EnsoZen3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;This enso is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:EnsoZen.png&quot;&gt;calligraphy of Kanjuro Shibata XX&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few weeks back, Trina asked about the meaning of the circles that have appeared on each week’s the sutra cards. In Zen we call this an enso (円相), which is simply the Japanese word for circle. My &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Shambhala-Dictionary-Buddhism-Zen/dp/0877735204/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1441489790&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=zen+dictionary&quot;&gt;Zen dictionary&lt;/a&gt; says it represents the absolute, the true reality and Wikipedia says it represents “enlightenment, strength, elegance, the universe and the void.” Then again, maybe it is just a circle. Nothing special.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drawing them is good Zen practice. Too much thinking and you get a squiggly circle. Just doing without practice also leads to uninspired results. Some discipline is required.
Give it a try. Get the right amount of ink on the brush; have the right pressure on the brush; be aware of the paper, the brush, the ink, you—then out flows an enso.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/posts/2015/06/enso.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/posts/2015/06/enso.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
